<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Rob's Cogitations]]></title>
  <link href="http://rob.cogit8.org/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rob.cogit8.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-27T11:57:06-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://rob.cogit8.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rob Hudson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Celery's Canvas to Reduce Elasticsearch Index Time]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob.cogit8.org/blog/2014/11/using-celerys-canvas-to-reduce-elasticsearch-index-time/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-27T11:43:05-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob.cogit8.org/blog/2014/11/using-celerys-canvas-to-reduce-elasticsearch-index-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We use <a href="http://www.elasticsearch.org/">Elasticsearch</a> for our backend search on
the <a href="https://marketplace.firefox.com/">Firefox Marketplace</a>. Most of
Marketplace APIs that drive the front-end only query Elasticsearch and never
hit the database. Because of this we have a few ways that we keep our
Elasticsearch index in sync with our database as changes happen. One of those
ways is a complete reindex of all database records into Elasticsearch.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>We don?t do a full reindex often but when we do we have a few ways to minimize
the impact on the Marketplace. The main way is to use index aliases which
allows us to create a brand new search index, push all of our data into it, and
when it is finished we point the alias to this new index.</p>

<p>When the Marketplace was first starting a full reindex would take minutes. As
time progressed and more fields were added to our documents and more apps were
added a full reindex was starting to take up to 40 minutes. So we started
investigating ways to speed this up again.</p>

<p>Our original implementation would do something like the following:</p>

<ol>
<li>Set up the new index</li>
<li>Query all apps we want to index retrieving the id only</li>
<li>Chunk the list of ids into sets</li>
<li>Send those sets of ids to celery to execute an indexing task on that set of ids</li>
<li>After the last task is complete, do some final optimizations on the index and swap aliases</li>
</ol>


<p>When the celery tasks were first written the Celery
<a href="http://celery.readthedocs.org/en/latest/userguide/canvas.html#the-primitives">canvas primitives</a>
that arrived with Celery v3.0 didn?t exist so the indexing tasks (step 4 above)
were being done serially.</p>

<p>After a bit of refactoring I updated the task chain to be simpler and also take
advantage of Celery?s primitives. The steps are the same but the indexing tasks
are now done in parallel.</p>

<p>One of the challenges was how to execute the follow-up task but only after all
the indexing tasks were completed. That?s where the new primitive <code>chord</code> comes
into play. A <code>chord</code> is a <code>group</code> with a callback, and a <code>group</code> takes a list
of tasks and applies them in parallel. We also need <code>chain</code> for the set up. Our
celery tasks are now broken down like this:</p>

<ol>
<li>Pre-index: Create new index</li>
<li>Indexing: Index all the sets of apps</li>
<li>Post-index: Optimize the index and swap aliases</li>
</ol>


<p>With the celery primitives it looks something like:</p>

<pre><code>chain(pre_index, chord(indexing, post_index))
</code></pre>

<p>When this finally landed on our production machines our full reindex time went
from 40 minutes or more down to just under 3 minutes. This was a bigger
improvement than I was expecting. Elasticsearch handles the flood of incoming
data like a champ too.</p>

<p>Another challenge was that Celery chords and running with
<code>CELERY_ALWAYS_EAGER=True</code> don?t get along, so if this setting is set we still
serialize the indexing tasks. Many of the Marketplace developers use this
setting to avoid having to run RabbitMQ and Celery locally.</p>

<p>This is the primary
<a href="https://github.com/mozilla/zamboni/commit/721a8cf409be5c1e4abd1ded44d5cfaff8c27e53">changeset</a>,
or view the Django management command
<a href="https://github.com/mozilla/zamboni/blob/master/lib/es/management/commands/reindex.py">reindex</a>
in its entirety.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Testing My New Jekyll Based Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://rob.cogit8.org/blog/2014/10/testing-my-new-jekyll-based-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-31T10:57:42-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rob.cogit8.org/blog/2014/10/testing-my-new-jekyll-based-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is just a test of this blog which uses Octopress and Github pages.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
