<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Data>
  <Series>
    <seriesid>73739</seriesid>
    <language>en</language>
    <SeriesName>Lost</SeriesName>
    <banner>graphical/73739-g4.jpg</banner>
    <Overview>After their plane, Oceanic Air flight 815, tore apart
    whilst thousands of miles off course, the survivors find
    themselves on a mysterious deserted island where they soon find
    out they are not alone.</Overview>
    <FirstAired>2004-09-22</FirstAired>
    <Network>ABC</Network>
    <IMDB_ID>tt0411008</IMDB_ID>
    <zap2it_id>SH672362</zap2it_id>
    <id>73739</id>
  </Series>
  <Series>
    <seriesid>160821</seriesid>
    <language>en</language>
    <SeriesName>Spain - Paradise Lost</SeriesName>
    <banner>graphical/160821-g.jpg</banner>
    <FirstAired>2009-06-17</FirstAired>
    <id>160821</id>
  </Series>
  <Series>
    <seriesid>80595</seriesid>
    <language>en</language>
    <SeriesName>Lost (UK)</SeriesName>
    <banner>graphical/80595-g.jpg</banner>
    <Overview>Of all the numerous reality game shows that enveloped
    British TV in the wake of Big Brother, Lost was one of the
    least publicised, low key, and most entertaining. The premise
    was ultra-simple. Three pairs of contestants were abandoned,
    blindfolded, somewhere in the world armed only with a meagre
    amount of possessions and a limited ration of local currency.
    They'd no idea where they'd been taken, and were deliberately
    deposited in as desolate, inhospitable and lonely environment
    as possible. They then had to get back to London as quickly as
    possible, and the first team home won a bottle of champagne -
    plus the chance to do it all again next week. Various elements
    combined to make the participants' respective journeys hugely
    enjoyable television. There was our sometimes gruesomely
    intimate insight into the relationships between team members,
    as they worked with but often against each other and squabbled
    constantly over how to make progress. The isolation aspect was
    intensely tangible. Aside from just one solitary cameraman -
    who themselves often became part of the drama - each pair were
    utterly alone, and you really felt it. Then there was the fact
    it was a desperately tense race against time. For every
    nonchalant easy-going contestant there was another absolutely
    determined to win at all costs. Finally Lost showcased a
    hilariously haphazard style of globetrotting, involving chaotic
    hitching and hiking across whole continents to the utter
    bemusement of their inhabitants. A potent mix of
    fly-on-the-wall showmanship and epic adventure, Lost was an
    exceptional show unfairly tucked away late at night that always
    managed to impress and excite.</Overview>
    <FirstAired>2007-09-27</FirstAired>
    <Network>Channel 4</Network>
    <id>80595</id>
  </Series>
  <Series>
    <seriesid>72906</seriesid>
    <language>en</language>
    <SeriesName>Lost (2001)</SeriesName>
    <banner>graphical/72906-g.jpg</banner>
    <Overview>Three pairs of globe-trotting strangers must work
    together to be the first team to reach the Statue of Liberty
    from a secret drop location. The winners will split the prize
    of $200,000. Over the life of the series, two different
    adventures were scheduled to take place.</Overview>
    <FirstAired>2001-09-01</FirstAired>
    <Network>NBC</Network>
    <zap2it_id>SH446649</zap2it_id>
    <id>72906</id>
  </Series>
  <Series>
    <seriesid>118101</seriesid>
    <language>en</language>
    <SeriesName>Heaven's Lost Property</SeriesName>
    <AliasNames>Misplaced by Heaven|Lost Property of the Sky|Sora
    no Otoshimono Forte|Sora no Otoshimono</AliasNames>
    <banner>graphical/118101-g3.jpg</banner>
    <Overview>Sakurai Tomoki is a normal student whose motto is
    "Normal is the best". If there is one thing abnormal, it is
    that he often dreams of a girl whose face he cannot even
    remember, and when he wakes up from that dream, he would always
    be crying. He tried leaving it as just a dream... but one day,
    from the sky, an angel descended.</Overview>
    <FirstAired>2009-10-05</FirstAired>
    <Network>TV Asahi</Network>
    <IMDB_ID>tt1528567</IMDB_ID>
    <id>118101</id>
  </Series>
  <Series>
    <seriesid>259632</seriesid>
    <language>en</language>
    <SeriesName>Mob City</SeriesName>
    <AliasNames>L.A. Noir|Lost Angels</AliasNames>
    <banner>graphical/259632-g5.jpg</banner>
    <Overview>The true story of a decades-long conflict between the
    Los Angeles Police Department, under the determined leadership
    of Police Chief William Parker, and ruthless criminal elements
    led by Mickey Cohen, a one-time boxer who rose to the top of
    L.A.'s criminal world. The series is a fast-paced crime drama
    set in Los Angeles during the 1940s and '50s. It's a world of
    glamorous movie stars, powerful studio heads, returning war
    heroes, a powerful and corrupt police force and an even more
    dangerous criminal network determined to make L.A. its West
    Coast base.</Overview>
    <FirstAired>2013-12-04</FirstAired>
    <Network>TNT</Network>
    <IMDB_ID>tt2176609</IMDB_ID>
    <zap2it_id>EP01816301</zap2it_id>
    <id>259632</id>
  </Series>
  <Series>
    <seriesid>79616</seriesid>
    <language>en</language>
    <SeriesName>Lost Worlds, Vanished Lives</SeriesName>
    <banner>graphical/79616-g.jpg</banner>
    <Overview>The study of rocks and their ancient secrets was
    something of a boyhood passion for David Attenborough. In these
    programmes, his enthusiasm for the subject is undiminished.
    With the help of expert palaeontologists, fossil hunters and
    (for the time) modern animation techniques, Attenborough
    attempts to show how life evolved in Earth's distant past. To
    do so, he travels the globe to visit the world's most famous
    fossil sites.</Overview>
    <FirstAired>1989-04-23</FirstAired>
    <Network>BBC</Network>
    <IMDB_ID>tt0764075</IMDB_ID>
    <id>79616</id>
  </Series>
</Data>
